Carlos,
(كارلوس)،
the Vietnam vet Marine
محارب البحرية القديم في حرب فيتنام
who volunteered for three tours and got shot up in every one.
الذي تطوع لثلاث جولات وأصيب بطلق ناري في كلٍ منها.
In 1971, he was medically retired
في عام 1971، أحيل إلى التقاعد بسبب حالته الطبيه
because he had so much shrapnel in his body
ولأن جسمه كان مليئاً بالشظايا
that he was setting off metal detectors.
لدرجة أنه كان يطلقُ عمل الأجهزة الكاشفة للمعادن.
For the next 42 years, he suffered from nightmares,
وعلى مدى 42 عامًا، عانى من الكوابيس،
extreme anxiety in public,
والقلق الشديد في الأماكن العامة.
isolation, depression.
والوحدة والإكتئاب.
He self-medicated with alcohol.
عالج نفسه عن طريق تناوله الخمور.
He was married and divorced three times.
تزوج وتطلق ثلاث مرات.
Carlos had post-traumatic stress disorder.
عانى (كارلوس) من اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة.
Now, I became a psychologist to help mitigate human suffering,
الآن، أصبحت طبيبا نفسيًا أساعدُ في تخفيف المعاناة البشرية،
and for the past 10 years, my target has been the suffering caused by PTSD,
وكانت معاناة اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة هو هدفي على مدار العشر سنوات الماضية،
as experienced by veterans like Carlos.
كما حدث لقدامى المحاربين مثل (كارلوس).
Until recently, the science of PTSD just wasn't there.
لم يكن لعلم اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة وجود إلا مؤخرا.
And so, we didn't know what to do.
وبالتالي لم نعرفُ ما يجبُ علينا القيام به.
We put some veterans on heavy drugs.
وصفنا لبعض قدامى المحاربين أدوية قوية.
Others we hospitalized and gave generic group therapy,
ووضعنا الآخرين في المستشفى وأخضعناهم لعلاج نفسي جماعي شامل،
and others still we simply said to them,
وقلنا ببساطة للآخرين:
"Just go home and try to forget about your experiences."
"اذهبوا لمنازلكم وحاولوا نسيان ما مررتم به."
More recently, we've tried therapy dogs, wilderness retreats --
ومؤخرًا، جربنا الكلاب المدربة لعهونهم، والعلاج القائم على المغامرات البرية --
many things which may temporarily relieve stress,
العديد من الأشياء التي قد تخففُ مؤقتًا من حدة التوتر،
but which don't actually eliminate PTSD symptoms over the long term.
ولكنها في الحقيقة لا تقضي على أعراض اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة على المدى البعيد.
But things have changed.
إلاّ أن الأمور قد تغيرت.
And I am here to tell you that we can now eliminate PTSD,
و أنا هنا لأقول لكم أننا نستطيع الآن القضاء على اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة،
not just manage the symptoms,
ليس فقط علاج الأعراض،
and in huge numbers of veterans.
لأعداد غفيرة من قدامى المحاربين.
Because new scientific research has been able to show,
لأن أبحاثا علمية جديدة تمكنت من الكشف
objectively, repeatedly,
بشكل موضوعي ومتكرر،
which treatments actually get rid of symptoms and which do not.
عن أي العلاجات التي تمكنت بالفعل من التخلص من الأعراض و أيها لم تتمكن.
Now as it turns out,
وكما تبين الآن،
the best treatments for PTSD use many of the very same training principles
أنّ أفضل العلاجات لاضطراب ما بعد الصدمة تستخدم إلى حدٍ بعيد نفس مبادئ التدريب
that the military uses in preparing its trainees for war.
التي تستخدمها المؤسسة العسكرية في إعداد مدربيها لخوض الحرب.
Now, making war --
حاليًا، شن الحروب--
this is something that we are good at.
هو شيءٌ نبرعُ فيه.
We humans have been making war since before we were even fully human.
قمنا كبشر بشن الحروب حتى قبل أن تكتمل إنسانيتنا.
And since then, we have gone from using stone and sinew
ومنذ ذلك الوقت، انتقلنا من استخدام الحجارة والقوة العضلية
to developing the most sophisticated and devastating weapon systems imaginable.
إلى تطوير أكثر أنظمة السلاح تقدمًا وتدميرًا التي يمكنُ تخيلها.
And to enable our warriors to use these weapons,
ولتمكين مقاتلينا من استخدام هذه الأسلحة،
we employ the most cutting-edge training methods.
سخرنا أكثر طرق التدرييب تطورًا وحداثةً.
We are good at making war.
نحن بارعون في شن الحروب.
And we are good at training our warriors to fight.
كما أننا بارعون في تدريب محاربينا على القتال.
Yet, when we consider the experience of the modern-day combat veteran,
مع ذلك، عندما نأخذ تجربة قتال المحارب القديم في العصر الحديث
we begin to see that we have not been as good
نجد أننا لا نملك تلك البراعة
at preparing them to come home.
في تحضيرهم للعودة إلى الوطن.
Why is that?
ولمَ هذا؟
Well, our ancestors lived immersed in conflict,
حسناً، عاش أجدادنا في غمرٍ من الصراعات،
and they fought right where they lived.
وحاربوا حيث كانوا يقطنون.
So until only very recently in our evolutionary history,
لذلك حتى وقتٍ متأخر جدًا من تاريخنا التطوري،
there was hardly a need to learn how to come home from war,
نادرًا ما كان هناك حاجة لتعلم كيفية العودة إلى الوطن بعد الحرب،
because we never really did.
لأننا لم نفعل ذلك أبدًا.
But thankfully, today,
اليوم، ولحسن الحظ،
most of humanity lives in far more peaceful societies,
تعيش البشرية في مجتمعات أكثر أمنًا،
and when there is conflict, we, especially in the United States,
وحيث يكونُ هناك صراع، نحنُ ولا سيما في أمريكا
now have the technology to put our warriors through advanced training,
لدينا التقنية اللازمة لوضع مقاتلينا ضمن برنامج تدريب متقدّم،
drop them in to fight anywhere on the globe
وإنزالهم إلى أية معركة في العالم
and when they're done,
وعند الانتهاء من عملهم،
jet them back to peacetime suburbia.
نعيدهم إلى الضواحي الهادئة.
But just imagine for a moment what this must feel like.
لكن تخيلوا للحظة واحدة، كيف يكون شعورهم.
I've spoken with veterans who've told me
تحدثتُ مع قدامى المحاربين الذين قالوا لي
that one day they're in a brutal firefight in Afghanistan
أنهم يوماً ما كانوا في معركة وحشية في أفعانستان
where they saw carnage and death,
حيث شاهدوا المذابح والموت،
and just three days later, they found themselves
وبعد ثلاثة أيام فقط، وجدوا أنفسهم
toting an ice chest to their kid's soccer game.
ينقلوا صناديق ثلج إلى مباراة كرة القدم الخاصة بأطفالهم
"Mindfuck" is the most common term.
"العبث بالعقل" هو المصطلح الأكثر شيوعًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's the most common term I've heard to describe that experience.
إنه المصطلح الأكثر شيوعًا والذي سمعته لوصف هذه التجربة.
And that's exactly what that is.
وهو هكذا تمامًا.
Because while our warriors spend countless hours training for war,
لأنه وبينما يقضي جنودنا ساعات لا تعد في التدريب للحرب،
we've only recently come to understand
استطعنا للتو فهم
that many require training on how to return to civilian life.
أن الكثير منهم يحتاجُ للتدريب على كيفية العودة للحياة المدنية.
Now, like any training, the best PTSD treatments require repetition.
الآن، مثل أي تدريب، تتطلب أفضل علاجات اضطراب بعد الصدمة التكرار.
In the military,
في العسكرية،
we don't simply hand trainees Mark-19 automatic grenade launchers
لا نسلّم المجندين بأيديهم قاذفات قنابل "Mark-19" الآلية بكل بساطة
and say, "Here's the trigger, here's some ammo and good luck."
ونقول لهم، "هاكم الزناد وبعض الذخيرة وحظاً موفقًا".
No. We train them, on the range and in specific contexts,
لا، بل ندربهم في حالات محددة وعلى نطاق واسع
over and over and over
مراراً وتكراراً
until lifting their weapon and engaging their target
حتى يصبحُ حملهم لسلاحهم وتحديدهم لأهدافهم
is so engrained into muscle memory
منغرسًا في ذاكرتهم العضلية بشكل جيد
that it can be performed without even thinking,
وقابلًا للتنفيذ حتى دون تفكير مسبق،
even under the most stressful conditions you can imagine.
وحتى في ظل أقسى الظروف توترًا والتي يصعبُ عليكم تخيلها،
Now, the same holds for training-based treatments.
الآن، يتمُ تطبيق نفس الشيء في العلاجات المبنية على التدريب.
The first of these treatments is cognitive therapy,
أول هذه العلاجات هو العلاج المعرفي،
and this is a kind of mental recalibration.
وهو نوع من إعادة قياس الصحة النفسية.
When veterans come home from war,
عندما يعود قدامى المحاربين من الحرب
their way of mentally framing the world is calibrated
يتمُ تشكل طريقة تفكيرهم العقلية للعالم
to an immensely more dangerous environment.
لبيئة أشد خطورة جدًا.
So when you try to overlay that mind frame onto a peacetime environment,
لذا عندما تحاولُ تقديم هذه العقلية المشكلة في بيئة آمنة،
you get problems.
ستواجه المشاكل.
You begin drowning in worries about dangers that aren't present.
ستغرق في الهموم حول المخاطر التي لا وجود لها أصلًا.
You begin not trusting family or friends.
وستبدأ في عدم الثقة في العائلة أو الأصدقاء
Which is not to say there are no dangers in civilian life; there are.
وهذا لا يعني عدم وجود مخاطر في الحياة المدنية.
It's just that the probability of encountering them
لكن احتمالية مواجهة المخاطر في الحياة المدنية
compared to combat
مقارنةً مع مخاطر المعركة
is astronomically lower.
هو قليل للغاية.
So we never advise veterans to turn off caution completely.
لهذا لا ننصح قدامى المحاربين أبداً أن يوقفوا حذرهم تمامًا.
We do train them, however, to adjust caution
مع ذلك، نحنُ ندربهم على ضبط الحذر
according to where they are.
وفقًا لمكان تواجدهم.
If you find yourself in a bad neighborhood,
إذا وجدت نفسك في جوارٍ سيء،
you turn it up.
ارفع حذرك.
Out to dinner with family?
وأنت في الخارج لتناول العشاء مع العائلة؟
You turn it way down.
قلل من حذرك.
We train veterans to be fiercely rational,
نحن ندرّب المحاربين القدامى ليكونوا عقلانيين بقوة،
to systematically gauge the actual statistical probability
لقياس منهجي لأرجحية الاحصاء الفعلي
of encountering, say, an IED here in peacetime America.
لمجابهة التعرض لعبوات ناسفة مرتجلة هنا في أمريكا في وقت السلم.
With enough practice, those recalibrations stick.
مع التدريب الكافي، تترسخ هذه القياسات.
The next of these treatments is exposure therapy,
ثاني هذه العلاجات هو العلاج بالتعرّض،
and this is a kind of field training,
وهو أشبه ما يكون بالتدريب الميداني،
and the fastest of the proven effective treatments out there.
والأسرع من العلاجات الفعالة المؤكدة في هذا المجال.
You remember Carlos?
أتذكرون كارلوس؟
This was the treatment that he chose.
كان هذا العلاج الذي اختاره.
And so we started off by giving him exercises,
وهكذا بدأنا بإعطائه التدريبات،
for him, challenging ones:
بالنسبة إليه، تدريبات تحدي:
going to a grocery store,
الذهاب إلى محل البقالة،
going to a shopping mall, going to a restaurant,
والذهاب إلى مركز التسوق، والذهاب إلى المطعم،
sitting with his back to the door.
والجلوس وظهره مواجه الباب.
And, critically --
والأهم --
staying in these environments.
البقاء في هذه الأجواء.
Now, at first he was very anxious.
الآن، في بداية الأمر كان كثير القلق
He wanted to sit where he could scan the room,
أراد أن يجلس حيثُ يمكنه تفحص الغرفة،
where he could plan escape routes,
وحيث يستطيع رسم خطة طرق الهروب،
where he could get his hands on a makeshift weapon.
وحيث يستطيع الحصول على سلاح مؤقت.
And he wanted to leave, but he didn't.
وأراد المغادرة، لكنه لم يفعل.
He remembered his training in the Marine Corps,
تذكّر تدريبه في قوات مشاة البحرية،
and he pushed through his discomfort.
وواصل طريقه خلال استياءه.
And every time he did this, his anxiety ratcheted down a little bit,
وفي كل مرة كان يفعلُ هذا، ينخفضُ قلقه تدريجيًا،
and then a little bit more and then a little bit more,
ثم أكثر قليلًا، وثم أكثر قليلًا.
until in the end,
حتى في النهاية،
he had effectively relearned how to sit in a public space
تعلّم من جديد وبفعالية كيفية الجلوس في الأماكن العامة
and just enjoy himself.
وبدأ يستمتع بما يفعل.
He also listened to recordings of his combat experiences,
استمعَ أيضاً إلى التسجيلات الصوتية لتجاربه الحربية،
over and over and over.
مراراً وتكراراً.
He listened until those memories no longer generated any anxiety.
ظل يسمعها حتى لم تعد هذه الذكريات تحدثُ له أي قلق.
He processed his memories so much
قام بالتعامل مع ذكرياته وتحويلها
that his brain no longer needed to return to those experiences
لدرجة لم يعد دماغه في حاجة إلى العودة لتلك التجارب
in his sleep.
في نومه.
And when I spoke with him a year after treatment had finished,
وحين تحدثت معه بعد سنة من انتهاء علاجه،
he told me,
أخبرني،
"Doc, this is the first time in 43 years
"دكتور، هذه أول مرة منذ 43 سنة
that I haven't had nightmares."
التي لم تداهمني فيها الكوابيس".
Now, this is different than erasing a memory.
الآن، هذا يختلف عن محو الذاكرة.
Veterans will always remember their traumatic experiences,
سيتذكر المحاربون القدامى دائماً تجاربهم الصادمة،
but with enough practice,
ولكن مع التدريب الكافي،
those memories are no longer as raw or as painful as they once were.
لم تعد تلك الذكريات واضحة أو مؤلمة كما كانت من قبل.
They don't feel emotionally like they just happened yesterday,
هُم لا يشعرون بحدة العواطف وكأنها حصلت بالأمس فقط،
and that is an immensely better place to be.
وهذا أفضل مكان ليكونوا فيه.
But it's often difficult.
لكنه غالبًا ما يكون صعبًا.
And, like any training, it may not work for everybody.
وكما في أي تدريب، قد لا يعمل الأمر مع الجميع.
And there are trust issues.
وهناك أمورًا بشأن الثقة.
Sometimes I'm asked,
يسألني الناس أحيانًا،
"If you haven't been there, Doc, how can you help me?"
"دكتور، كيف يمكنك مساعدتي إذا لم تكن هناك؟"
Which is understandable.
الذي هو أمرٌ مفهوم.
But at the point of returning to civilian life,
لكن عند العودة إلى الحياة المدنية،
you do not require somebody who's been there.
لا تحتاجُ شخصاً ليكون معك.
You don't require training for operations on the battlefield;
لا تحتاجُ تدريباً للعمليات في ساحة المعركة،
you require training on how to come home.
تحتاجُ تدريباً حول كيفية العودة إلى الوطن.
For the past 10 years of my work,
خلال العشر سنوات الماضية من عملي،
I have been exposed to detailed accounts
تعرضتُ لقصص مفصّلة
of the worst experiences that you can imagine,
عن أسوأ التجارب التي يمكن أن تتخيلوها،
daily.
ويومياً.
And it hasn't always been easy.
ولم يكن ذلك سهلًا دائمًا.
There have been times where I have just felt my heart break
كانت هناك أوقات شعرتُ فيها أن قلبي يتحطم
or that I've absorbed too much.
أو أنني استوعبتُ فوق طاقتي.
But these training-based treatments work so well,
لكن تعملُ هذه العلاجات المبنية على التدريب بشكلٍ جيد،
that whatever this work takes out of me, it puts back even more,
وكلما استنزف العمل من قوتي، عاد وخزّن المزيد من القوة،
because I see people get better.
لأنني أرى الناس تتحسن.
I see people's lives transform.
أرى حياتهم تتحول.
Carlos can now enjoy outings with his grandchildren,
يستطيع (كارلوس) الآن أن يستمتع بالنزهات مع أحفاده،
which is something he couldn't even do with his own children.
وهذا شيء لم يستطع حتى القيام به مع أطفاله.
And what's amazing to me is that after 43 years of suffering,
وما هو مدهش بالنسة لي، هو أنه بعد 43 سنة من المعاناة،
it only took him 10 weeks of intense training to get his life back.
استغرقه 10 أشهر فقط من التدريب المكثف ليستعيد حياته.
And when I spoke with him, he told me,
وعندما حدثته، قال لي،
"I know that I can't get those years back.
"أعلم أني لا أستطيع استرداد تلك السنوات.
But at least now, whatever days that I have left on this Earth,
لكن على الأقل الآن، مهما كانت الأيام المتبقية لي على هذه المعمورة،
I can live them in peace."
أستطيع أن أعيش بسلام."
He also said, "I hope that these younger veterans don't wait
قال أيضاً: "أتمنى ألا ينتظر هؤلاء المحاربون الشباب
to get the help they need."
الحصول على المساعدة التي يحتاجونها".
And that's my hope, too.
وهذه هي أمنيتي أيضاً.
Because ...
لأن ..
this life is short,
هذه الحياة قصيرة،
and if you are fortunate enough to have survived war
وإذا كنتَ محظوظاً بما فيه الكفاية للنجاة من الحرب
or any kind of traumatic experience,
أو أي نوع من التجربة الصادمة،
you owe it to yourself to live your life well.
تُدين بها لنفسك لتعيش حياتك كما يجب.
And you shouldn't wait to get the training you need
ويجب أن لا تنتظر للحصول على التدريب الذي تحتاجه
to make that happen.
لتحقيق ذلك.
Now, the best way of ending human suffering caused by war
الآن، أفضل طريقة لإنهاء معاناة الإنسان الناجمة عن الحرب،
is to never go to war.
هي عدم الذهاب إلى الحرب أبداً.
But we are just not there yet as a species.
لكننا لم نصل بعدُ إلى هناك كجنس بشري.
Until we are,
إلى ذلك الحين،
the mental suffering that we create in our sons and in our daughters
فالمعاناة الذهنية التي نصنعها في أبنائنا وبناتنا
when we send them off to fight
عندما نرسلهم إلى القتال
can be alleviated.
يمكنُ تخفيفها.
But we must ensure that the science, the energy level, the value
لكن يجب علينا أن نؤكد أن العلم ودرجة القوة والأهمية والقيمة
that we place on sending them off to war
التي نستثمرها على ارسالهم إلى الحرب
is at the very least mirrored
هي على أقل تقدير معكوسة
in how well we prepare them to come back home to us.
لكيفية تحضيرهم للعودة إلينا.
This much, we owe them.
نحن مدينون لهم بهذا القدر.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)